All right, so continuing with the supplemental lessons.
Let's briefly review the ESP IDF Riotous as a precursor to what's to come in the application development
lessons.
So the scope of this lesson won't be too exhaustive and will be limited to the following.
I'll show you where to find documentation if you want to go more in-depth into free photos, and then
we'll review some differences from the ESP IDF version of free autos with the vanilla or regular free
autos.
And then we'll take a look at Teske states test creation and the X Test Create Penta Core API and the
V task delay as well.
All right, so let's jump right in.
OK, so in the case that you're new to free autos, Free Autos is a real time operating system kernel
for embedded devices, and the following page from free auto storage provides a clear description of
an arthouse.
So to summarize, the scheduler in a Real-Time Operating System is designed to provide a predictable
execution pattern, and often embedded systems have real time requirements, which means that they must
respond to a certain event within a strictly defined time or deadline.
The guarantee to meet these requirements can only be made if the behavior of the operating system scheduler
can be predicted or is deterministic.
All right.
So you may want to bookmark this link for the free or books available from Free Autostart.
Org here.
They're nice to have as an additional resource.
And if you go to the free those fundamentals link, you'll find that this page contains background information
on multitasking and basic real time concepts, which is intended for beginners.
So if you want to get more into theory, this is also a good resource.
Additionally, you can find impressive documentation about their version of Free Artus by following
this link, and we'll take a look at parts of that shortly.
OK, so there are a few apparent differences between the aespa, ID3 autos and the regular or vanilla
free autos that affect the application development.
Firstly, the ESP 32 extends the MCU contains two extensive processor cores.
And the IDF uses its own version of the extensive port of frittatas, which provides multicore support.
And so in the case that you are already familiar with free autos, but not the IDF version, we do not
have to call the V task start schedule or API when using the ESP IDF free autos.
Also, the free autos task stack size is specified in bytes when using the IDF, not words as you would
do with regular free autos.
Additionally, the application Start-Up Flow is relevant here, which covers everything that happens
after the application starts executing and before the main function starts running inside the main task.
You can find details here with a high level view of the startup.
Process is described first.
The first stage bootloader and rom loads the second stage bootloader image to RAM from the Flash Offset
Hex one thousand and the second step.
The second stage bootloader loads the partition table and the main application image from Flash.
The main application incorporates both RAM segments and read on these segments via flash cache.
Then the application startup executes, and at this point, the second CPU and auto scheduler are started.
You can read up on the details of each of these steps, so feel free to come here if you're interested.
But for now, let's go over to the application startup details.
And so everything that happens after the application starts and before the app main is called involves
the following port initialization of hardware and Basic C runtime environment system, initialization
of software services and free autos, and running the main task and calling App Main, which will be
our application entry point.
All right, so I think that's enough details about the application startup for purposes.
OK, so in another toast implementation of a design, the program is divided into different tasks and
each task runs continuously in an infinite loop.
OK, so we can create free toast tasks using the X test, create APIs.
And to do that, we'll need to include free autos, slash tasks, storage.
And there are two API options available.
We can use X Test Create, which lets the ESP IDF riotous choose which core of the ESP thirty two to
the task should run on.
Then this is the basic structure of a free toast task with an infinite loop as the main body of the
task.
And here the X Task Create API creates the task.
And so its task rate pinned to core allows specifying which core the tasks should run on in the next.
I'll summarize the description of the API parameters.
All right, the first parameter PV test code is the custom C function or riotous task that runs in an
infinite loop.
And PC name is the descriptive name that you can give a task and is only used as a debugging aid.
US stack depth is the memory and bytes that should be allocated by the kernel to the task.
PV parameters is an optional parameter that is a pointer that can be used by the task.
UX priority is the priority at which the task should run on in the higher priority number takes precedence
and P created task is an optional task handle by which the created task can be referenced.
For example, if you need to use various free auto KPIs like V Task Delete, as shown here with the
task handle is referenced.
And then core idea is the core of the ESP 32 that the task is to be assigned to, which can be core
zero or core one.
And this link will take you to a description of task states as well as a state transition diagram.
OK, so let's take a look at the state diagram, and I'll briefly summarize the tasks states.
So the running state means that the task is executing and utilizing the processor and the ready state
here means that the task is able to execute but is not currently running because the task with an equal
or higher priority is currently running.
So if a task is blocked, this can be caused by a temporal event.
For example, a call to V task delay that causes the task to be placed into the block state until the
delay period has expired.
Or it can be blocked due to an external event, which means that the task is waiting to receive from
a Q event group or notification or a similar event.
And this differs from tasks in the suspended state where there is no timeout in tasks only enter and
exit the suspended state when explicitly commanded to do so using V tasks suspend and X task resume
API calls.
All right.
And these are linked.
So feel free to read up on those as well.
And about Vitesse DeLay, it's used to send a task into the black state for a set number of ticks.
The actual time that the task remains blocked depends on the tick rate and the constant port tick period.
Milliseconds can be used to calculate real time from the tick rate.
For example, if the free tortoise tick rate in the SDK config is set to 100 hertz as it's shown here,
then this port tick period is 10 milliseconds and 500 divided by 10 is 50 ticks, which is what we passed
to test delay and that is x delay.
In this example, and with 50 ticks at a period of 10 milliseconds, we end up with the five hundred
millisecond delay.
All right, so that's it for this quick overview of free autos.